When I first started at Cedric, it was a very small office, as it always had been.
I think there was a secretary, two other people and me.
And the reason that he took me on is that at that time he had just got the
InterAction
Centre as a project.
Work had commenced on it, not too far.
And I was a humble assistant.
which I thought was a very good project. As it turned out, it was the last thing he
actually
ever built, but no one knew that at the time. And Cedric was very interesting in
that because
Ed Berman, who was the client, who was an American but lived in London for a long
time,
and started off observing that there were... He came out of the theatre background
and
observing a lot of kids not going to school, hanging around on the streets.
So he started dressing up as a clown, pushing a street cart,
but the cart was full of toys and other games and other things.
It's like the Pied Piper of Hamelin, a little bit.
And then that was very popular and then he formalised it a bit and then more people
came in and the whole thing grew as a sort of
community action sort of group.
And it got to the point where
it was very successful. It had a city farm,
very early city farm, quite a common concept as you know, and they needed a new
building.
And the borough of Camden here in London, they said well you can have this piece of
land via railway until 2002, otherwise more or less a 25 year period. So it was not
a
lot of money but they raised a bit of money and that was interesting. So this was
during
a period of high inflation in the UK, very high inflation. So it was decided that,
this
is an important point because it suited Cedric perfectly, the money they had would
buy a
drainage system, a concrete slab and a steel frame. It was better to spend that
money now
because if you waited the price would go up significantly and therefore you would
always
be chasing the money. So you might as well spend what you had and then there can be
a
Of course, in effect, you had a one-to-one model of the building.
And I often think, and I'm sure Cedric thought,
that in a way it was more useful like that
than actually finishing the building.
Because Ed's outfit was a bit anarchic, I have to say,
and there was a high turnover of people.
So every two weeks, my job was to...
This was after the frame went up and everything.
My job was to go there and have a conversation with all the people in the different
departments.
There was silkscreen printing, there was car maintenance, there was some physical
exercise.
It was like a school and there was a pub in there.
We'd actually chalk out various areas on the ground and say, yeah, that's what I
want.
A month later, it would be somebody else in charge of silkscreen printing.
And you had different ideas.
So nothing really ever resolved itself on the plan.
And in the meantime, we were doing some of the details
in readiness for when they got the other money.
When it came to the details,
Cedric didn't have much to say about these things.
I was not exactly experienced either.
by that time the more experienced assistant at Cedric he had moved on, I found
myself
in charge of the project. And when I had a genuine question I'd say to Cedric in the
mornings, I've got an issue, he'd say I'll talk to you later about that, which meant
he never did talk to you about it, so you just had to sort of resolve it yourself.
The
one thing that he did, there were two things that he said to me which I think were
important.
which was related to the detailing, that everything you should take apart from the
steel frame,
everything else in the building you should be able to take apart with a standard
bicycle
spanner. I thought that was interesting. The other thing he said, never take a
decision
until you have to. Which I think was really good, I still think about that today.
Why
Why would you decide that you're going to do this when you don't have to take that
decision
because in a month it might look a bit different and then you do something else.
I think that's true.
It's one of the problems with getting planning permission.
Everything is so fixed that actually as you go on and evolve the detail of the
building
and you're actually in the process of building, it might be something much better to
do but
actually by law you're fixed to what you've already got permission for.
I probably last went to that building in the early 21st century, 2001, 2002.
Occasionally I like to go back, very occasionally.
No one ever changed anything.
And that was the reality.
And that has to make you think, and of course if Cedric had still been around then,
surely
he'd be thinking, you know, the notion of flexibility, uncertainty, and uncertainty
underpinned much of his thinking related to architecture in general. You had to
examine
that. You had to say, well, in the end, you don't need to move everything unless
it's
a real emergency or a complete change in thought because people in themselves are
really adaptable.
They can make anything out of anything. If I give you a couple of sheds put together
and a bit of a tent, you can live in it.
It's not a house, but it is a home.
And I think the same is true,
particularly when it came to a community centre.
However, the building itself was highly successful
and it was well used.
Whether people liked it or not, I don't know.
That didn't seem to be the point.
They used it and it performed a useful purpose.
But people of all ages, it wasn't just children,
It was all ages, because a lot of problems at that time in that part of London.
Did Cedric have a real interest in the build?
I've often pondered that, because he still had plenty of active life as an architect
left in him at that time.
He wasn't exactly short of contacts.
He was very well connected, and opportunities to build did come his way, or
requests.
But he didn't do it.
I mean, I think there was something, was it a greenhouse or something in Paris,
which failed, I think, for financial reasons.
I don't really know the story because it was after my time with him.
I think he was genuinely disappointed not to build that.
I think he really wanted to build that because he found that interesting.
But did he really want to build it?
And I've often pondered that question.
I think that he didn't really.
He enjoyed the conversations, he enjoyed the discussion around the project, he
enjoyed
clearly the discussion around architecture and what it meant in general and he was a
very good critic which is why he was very popular to come to juries here and many
other
places.
That's what he enjoyed and of course we all tend to pursue what we enjoy.
He didn't enjoy minutes of meetings, the possible legal aspects of building, the
minutiae of
the building regs.
These are all things which I think he just didn't want to do that.
The clue there was when I was asking him how to resolve a certain detail and I
couldn't
see him for dust.
He was off.
He was very critical of the school, but he would also participate in the school at
the same time.
He was always very critical of Alvin.
Very rude to us, just around the corner, about Alvin.
I thought, well, Alvin's not my best man in the world, but he's certainly not the
worst.
And I didn't understand that inevitably, without Alvin, this place would have
closed.
There's no doubt about it.
and he saved the school and it went on and did what it did.
Which is strange. So I think that Elvin,
sorry, I think that Cedric sometimes
deliberately set up people not as enemies but as
they were, they were, he was like
practicing in his own head, I think,
what he really thought about the education here at the school
and what he was doing. He had no intention of doing anything about it.
and he would come here and give the odd lecture and things but um and yeah i think
he's very happy
to do that sometimes students would go around and see him upstairs because obviously
in the
upstairs around the corner i say upstairs because he had the room at the top of his
office his
office is on one two three floors first second and fourth floor and the top floor
was the white
room or also known as East Grinstead. It was called East Grinstead so that if
somebody
called for him and the secretary said, I'm sorry, he's in East Grinstead, she wasn't
actually telling a lie, but actually he was upstairs, but there was no phone link up
there.
He would disappear up there for a long time with his sketchbook, the newspapers, the
brandy
and the cigar. The McAlpines were worried, the organisation, that they had to do
something
about the conditions of building sites. Otherwise it becomes an unattractive job and
they wouldn't
be able to get the employees to work, particularly in central London sites. So by
that time if
you were working in Mayfair on site, let's say people working on building sites at
lunchtime
would go and have a drink in the pub. It wouldn't happen today. They found that they
were not
allowed to go into the pub because of the way that they were dressed. So we looked
at
all the aspects of the clothes, ripping off stuff so you could actually look
alright,
so you could go to the pub if you wanted to.
It was really the beginning of blue jeans in terms of as part of your working outfit
and with a lot of talking to experts.
Young men working on building sites in the cult in blue jeans would actually suffer
later in life
arthritis and other things because it's not the right clothing to wear.
When I first started at Cedric, the office hours were 10 o'clock in the morning
until 6.
And that suited me just fine. Not too early.
And that worked well. Very often you'd arrive in the morning
and just sit down and get on with whatever you were doing.
And Cedric, he had a small compartment on the main floor,
on the second floor, where reception also was.
And he would sit there and he would take phone calls there.
So he would do all his phone calls in the morning
and then when he finished those phone calls,
he would go upstairs to the white room or East Gwynstead.
And he would then, but it was in that gap between phone calls and going upstairs
that
his son talked to you.
Not necessarily about what you were doing, but anything that he was thinking.
And we discussed things that were in journals and other aspects.
And he was a great one for anecdotes.
But of course every man particularly, more than women, as they get older they like
anecdotes.
because actually it's good. I find I do it myself with my own employees.
And because it's a way of learning, it's a way of sort of passing on things.
When we got to 1976, which was a famously very hot summer here in London,
his office had large windows. It wasn't very big, facing east and south.
No air conditioning, of course.
And by the time it got to two o'clock in the afternoon, you couldn't work in the
office.
I mean it was just unbearable. So I had this idea, I said look, why don't we start
at 7
o'clock in the morning and just work for seven hours and go home at 2, because it
would be
better. He loved that because it was playing with time. He was always interested in
the
concept of time and therefore you're playing with time in the context of the office.
And
that's what we did. It was a real struggle getting there at 7, but you get used to
it
after a while. And it clearly was a struggle for the Secretary to get there at 7,
but he
wanted to be there before you, to make a point. It always amused me. So he'd arrive
and there
he was, but he was out of breath, he'd just run up the stairs.
What was the Hot Stuff Club? It was an excuse to drink, I think, and it involved
Patricia
Dawkins, who was the Secretary for quite a long time, who was a very nice girl, lots
of fun and I think the Hot Stuff Club involved certainly Frank Newby and David
Alford. I
think the then leader of the Trade Union Congress was also a part of it and they had
to have
a woman and that was Patricia. Us young men were kept well away from the Hot Stuff
Club.
from the Hot Stuff Club. But just to go back to Trode, brother, and the White Room,
when
there was celebration, I mean he loved birthdays and any reason to celebrate
something. Or
it might be the 21st birthday of the office, I think that might have been the Smarty
incident
in the White Room. So it was a big party and the umbrellas which were filled with
Smarties
and you opened them and they fell everywhere. I can't remember much else but Trode
also
loved board games and there was a fairly new board game at the time called Escape
from
Cold Dits and we'd have evenings where we would play this and Trode would actually,
But actually all the food was all tied up in brown paper and bits of string.
And he always had to be the Nazi.
Because I think he had a helmet and jackboots.
And you had to have the Nazi.
And everyone else was sort of dressed up in old clothes with bits of string around
you
as though you were escaping from a prison camp.
And then there was lots of drink.
But then he had to drink the wine out of old tin mugs and everything.
It was all nicely done, just under one low watt light bulb that was bare.
It was a horrible light.
It was all about effect and having fun.
It was about removing yourself from all the other stuff you were doing in the day.
It was an alternative life.
In some ways, I think the White Room was an alternative life.
It was certainly a retreat.
It was a place to think about other things and to do other things.
And of course, I'm sure if Cedric was here and you asked him what was the White
Room,
that's where I did my work. But he did much more than that up there, much more.
You can understand the statement as to the role of the architect as being to enable
things
in a number of practical ways. I mean, he always said that if somebody asked an
architect
design a new house, maybe it's a divorce that's required. So it's always looking
behind the
reasons as to why you think you need a new building. So if there's any way of not
building
a building and solving this problem. So it's very much, I mean, at that time when I
came
into that, when I was a student here, people like Karl Popper were very influential
in
the whole idea of problem solving. But of course, later in life, and I came to this
conclusion as well. You think, well, you can't characterize architecture as simply
being
problem solving because lots of other people can solve problems. Architecture is
certainly
something else. Don't ask me what. Don't, you dare. But there is something else and
that's why it's not always about solving problems. But at that time, Cedric would
have said,
Every day in the newspaper there is a series of things that architects could
address, because
there are problems if you read a news article in a particular way.
There's an architectural solution, but architecture in the widest sense of the word.
So the role as an enabler was certainly a part of his vocabulary and part of his
attitude.
I think to a certain extent Cedric's major preoccupation sounds cruel, but it's
actually
quite good, was himself, I have to say. I think he was very aware of who he was, his
background and how respected he was, but all being it, albeit, it was a very
particular
taste which didn't suit everyone. You can't imagine Cedric Price having a
conversation
with Richard Meyer, can you, because it was chalk and cheese. I think that I often
wonder
if he, with Joan Littlewood, had actually built the Fun Palace,
what that might have changed in his life.
I think he was very disappointed in particular that that project never occurred.
Because again, it was the perfect project for him,
and she was the perfect client as well,
because she was completely mad, in a good way.
She was very inventive, she was trying to invent what theatre was
and how theatre was delivered to the general public
and what the role of the public was and the audience was and different ways of doing
it.
Which was perfect for Cedric because that's what he's trying to do with architecture
and building.
And everything was a question mark and unresolved. I think that lack of resolution
was an important
part of the work. Had he built it, of course, I don't know. I think he was, and I
get angry as
well you know that the Santa Pompidou would not be as it was without without
the fun pass and I get angry about that not because I mean it's what one thing
leads to another we don't own any ideas you know once you've talked about an
idea it's belongs to the world but Richard Rogers and piano have never
really acknowledged Cedric public as far as I know I've never heard them make any
reference. I can never imagine how they could do that without referring to
precedents. It
didn't come out of nowhere, for example. So I think that Cedric was quite
disappointed,
quite offended by that, that he had done a lot of groundwork. It was very
interesting
at the time. That's why it was well published and well known by a wide range of
people.
And then the Popadou Center comes. Well, I mean, that's it. It's not it. I mean, it
would
have been very different had Cedric been doing but there was an aesthetic based in
there.
I mean I think that there were other things going on at the time which you had to,
all
the test rigs for the vertical takeoff aircraft, it's called the flying bedstead,
looked like
the Fun Palace. I mean really did. But that's the whole thing, it's a sort of test
bed for
trying something out and it's exactly the same philosophy with buildings in a way
the
InterAction Centre which I've already discussed, in a way was a test bed for trying
something
out. The problem there was it really wasn't the right people with the right kind
of...
they had lots of energy but not energy for that in the actual building. Did that
matter?
Not really. I think the McAfee project was also a perfect project for Cedric. It was
about making life better for a particular set of people in terms of food, clothes,
safety,
health and safety. He was very quickly on to health and safety. I don't know what he
thought later in life when health and safety had become a menace, but nonetheless,
the
idea of saving life, having conditions, it's actually good for humanity. I think
that was
important to him. In a way Cedric's role is a sort of conscience really,
particularly
to other architects, maybe to others as well. Often when I'm thinking about a new
project,
fiddling around and scratching my head, sometimes I feel Cedric sitting on my
shoulder like
some sort of parrot and says, don't do that. How dare you think that. In a way I
think
quite a good role, I'm very happy with that, very thankful for it. And for a long
time,
you know, I've been teaching in Vienna for quite a while, you know, I occasionally
bring
up Cedric in conversation. A whole body of students never heard of him, had no idea
who
Cedric Price was, which I found a bit upsetting. I found in the last five to six
years in particular
Now students come up to me and say, you used to work for Cedric.
And they wanted a conversation. In much the same way as they're very aware of
Archigram. Archigram went completely out of fashion I suppose
in some way, or out of the consciousness of the younger architect.
They're now back in and I think that
I always take that, which would be a certain compliment
to Cedric, is that the more interesting students
gone beyond the idea of style. Where it's going is a whole other film that we might
make in the future. But I think that's good. There's no assumptions, really. I think
that's
a good attitude to maintain.